Ao LIU

Ph.D. in Computer Science



Cambridge, MA

Summary

Research Machine Learning (Recommendation Systems, Learning to Rank, Algorithm Design, etc.),

Interests Differential Privacy, Computational Social Choice, and Quantum Computation

Experience 1+ years of industry experience in personalization, recommendation systems, LLM, theoretical

computer science, differential privacy, and adversarial robustness

Academia Published 20+ papers and received 250+ citations to date.

Reviewed 50+ papers for top AI conferences or journals.

Education

01/2018 – 05/2023 Ph.D. in Computer Science, Rensselaer Polytechnic Institute (RPI) Troy, NY

Thesis: Group Decision Makings from Partial Preferences [Link]

08/2015 – 05/2018 M.Eng. in Material Engineering, Rensselaer Polytechnic Institute (RPI) Troy, NY

Research Focus: Optics and Polymer Physics

08/2010 – 05/2014 **B.S. in Mathematics and Physics,** Tsinghua University Beijing, China Minor in Computer Technology, and in Academic Talent Program

Experience

07/2023 – Present Software Engineer at Google Core ML Mountain View, CA

Design and Research More Efficient Transformers for Recommendation Systems

05/2022 - 08/2022 Research Intern at Google Core ML Mountain View, CA

Project: A More Accurate Position Bias Estimator for Unbiased Learning to Rank

 \odot Significant accuracy improvement (${\sim}8\%)$ v.s. state-of-the-art without extra computational resources.

Proposed a more accurate model for position bias in recommendation systems. (user-modeling)
Designed a new machine learning framework based on the proposed position bias model and

- Designed a new machine learning framework based on the proposed position bias model and two-tower model. (algorithm design, statistics)

- Implemented a data pipeline to extract the required features from data. (C/C++)

- Implemented the machine learning framework, tested on Yahoo! dataset and integrated it into Google codebase. (Python, TensorFlow, Google Test)

08/2018 – 12/2018 Visiting Scholar at MIT-IBM Watson AI Lab

Project: Certifiably Robust Interpretation via Rényi Differential Privacy

05/2019 - 08/2019 \circ Significant robustness improvement (\sim 12%) plus accuracy improvement v.s. state-of-the-art.

- Yes! We improved both robustness and accuracy at the same time! Note that accuracy and robustness are trade-offs in machine learning.

- Theoretically connected Rényi differential privacy and interpretation robustness.

- Designed a new robust algorithm to interpret neural networks for image classifications.

- Implemented the proposed robust algorithm and tested it on VOC2007 dataset for various properties, including robustness, accuracy, and computational efficiency. (*Python*, *PyTorch*, *TorchRay*, *TensorFlow*)

O Delivered one academic paper (on top AI journal) and two patents.

Skills

and

Implementation Programming languages: Python, C/C++, MATLAB

Tools and platforms: TensorFlow, PyTorch, TorchRay, LATEX, GoogleTest

Design/ Theory Algorithm design, Statistics, Time/Sample-complexity analysis, User-modeling, Markov chain Mount-Carlo (MCMC), Differential privacy analysis, Robustness analysis, Model identifiability.

Review Services

Journal Information Sciences, TMLR, ACM ToIS, Sankhya B

Conference NeurIPS (20,21,22&23), ICML (22,23&24), ICLR (23&24), AAAI (21&22), IJCAI-22

TMLR	Smoothed Differential Privacy [PDF] <u>Ao Liu</u> , Yu-Xiang Wang, and Lirong Xia
UAI-23	Accelerating Voting by Quantum Computation [PDF] <u>Ao Liu</u> , Qishen Han, Lirong Xia, and Nengkun Yu
AIJ	Certifiably Robust Interpretation via Rényi Differential Privacy [Link] [ArXiv] <u>Ao Liu</u> , Xiaoyu Chen, Sijia Liu, Lirong Xia, and Chuang Gan Also in proceedings of AAAI-23 Journal Track (oral presentation)
AAAI-23 (oral)	Differentially Private Condorcet Voting [PDF] Zhechen Li, <u>Ao Liu</u> , Lirong Xia, Yongzhi Cao, and Hanpin Wang
AAAI-22	The Semi-Random Likelihood of Doctrinal Paradoxes [PDF] $\underline{Ao\ Liu}$, and Lirong Xia
IJCAI-22 (oral)	Learning Mixtures of Random Utility Models with Features from Incomplete Preferences [PDF] Zhibing Zhao, <u>Ao Liu</u> , and Lirong Xia
JAIR	Learning to Design Fair and Private Voting Rules [PDF] Farhad Mohsin, <u>Ao Liu</u> , Pin-Yu Chen, Francesca Rossi, and Lirong Xia
UAI-20 (oral)	How Private Are Commonly-Used Voting Rules? [PDF] Farhad Mohsin, <u>Ao Liu</u> , Pin-Yu Chen, Francesca Rossi, and Lirong Xia
ETRA-20 $Adjunct$	Let It Snow: Adding Pixel Noise to Protect the Users Identity [Link] Brendan John, <u>Ao Liu</u> , Lirong Xia, Sanjeev Koppal, and Eakta Jain
AAAI-19 (oral)	Near-Neighbor Methods in Random Preference Completion [PDF] <u>Ao Liu</u> , Qiong Wu, Zhenming Liu, and Lirong Xia
AAAI-19 (oral)	Learning Plackett-Luce Mixture from Partial Preferences [PDF] <u>Ao Liu</u> , Zhibing Zhao, Chao Liao, Pinyan Lu, and Lirong Xia
ETRA-19 (oral)	Differential Privacy for Eye-Tracking Data [PDF] <u>Ao Liu</u> , Lirong Xia, Andrew Duchowski, Reynold Bailey, Kenneth Holmqvist, and Eakta Jain
US Patent	Certifiably Robust Interpretation [PDF] <u>Ao Liu</u> , Sijia Liu, Bo Wu, Lirong Xia, Qi Cheng Li, and Chuang Gan
US Patent	Interpretation Maps with Guaranteed Robustness [PDF] <u>Ao Liu</u> , Sijia Liu, Abhishek Bhandwaldar, Chuang Gan, Lirong Xia, and Qi Cheng Li
	Awards and Teaching
09/2019 - 05/2022	RPI-IBM AI Horizon Scholarship 3-year scholarship supported by Rensselaer-IBM Artificial Intelligence Research Collaboration
09/2016 - 05/2017	RPI Presidential Graduate Research Fellowship A One-Year Fellowship for Outstanding Graduate Students [Certificate]
Spring 2023	Teaching Assistant of CSCI 4150: Introduction to AI Instructor: Lirong Xia
04/2021	Guest Lecture at CSCI 4967/6967: Economics and Computation Topic: The Semi-Random Likelihood of Doctrinal Paradoxes

Spring 2023 Teaching Assistant of MATH 1020: Calculus II

Instructor: David A. Schmidt

Selected Publication